foreign
[Music]
welcome to another episode of Shake
sales I'm your host Maggie Bloom the
sales evangelist at mailshake and today
we are speaking with billel petrawi and
he's the founder of death to fluff he's
a Salesforce top sales influencer and a
LinkedIn sales star Philo is also
amazing when it comes to sales tips for
the community so I'm going to read off
the screen for the people who are
looking right here but I just found this
awesome quote on his profile that
someone said I stumbled across your
posts and community and this stuff is
amazing I've learned more in 30 seconds
than weeks of training it's candid and
realistic and not robotic so I'm super
excited to talk with him a little bit
today about death to fluff when it comes
to cold calling so billel thank you so
much for being here today do you mind
taking some time to introduce yourself
yeah it's a pleasure thank you for
having me Maggie it's uh always an honor
to do this sort of stuff I I don't know
where that quote came from that that
hyped me up a bit too much but temper
expectations folks yeah
I'm not a miracle worker but that's
awesome glad somebody found value in it
um yeah my background I've been a part
of seven startups and pretty much the
first sales hire at all of them and so
when you're in that kind of situation
where you're at some no-name startup
competing against some Behemoth and I've
competed against the big boys like
LinkedIn IBM and the major major brands
uh you gotta be resourceful you gotta be
Scrappy you got to be a little bit
cheeky uh you can't do what the founders
did when they closed their first couple
customers as a seller you gotta you
can't sell quite like that so it's hard
Lessons Learned and I'm glad I'm glad
they're valuable for others when I share
them
yeah I think it's I think it's a
different type of selling mentality I
always tell people it's like try selling
something where people have never even
heard your name before like mailshake
the other company I worked at was
Roadrunner
you've probably been in those situations
like you said seven times where you're
just trying to tell people about what
you're doing in general too or what the
company is yeah it's It's Tricky it's
very tricky and there and there are some
proven methods it's it's not just like
uh an art or something like that there's
definitely a science to it there are
some proven methods to it and um over
the years I've Had The Good Fortune of
doing a lot of different sales trainings
but I will say as each of them had their
own benefits there was a lot of gaps
there's a lot of things that they didn't
teach me that I wish they did and that's
really what I try to post about is all
those things that if I could go back in
time 13 years ago I would tell myself
here you go XYZ one two three yeah
you're gonna have a much better time
selling now that you know that
so you didn't get like you said there's
there's gaps in the training that you've
had and you've got on through different
set like sales training programs so
where did you learn about you know
what's brought you here today and what
you post about on LinkedIn a lot of it
actually comes from non-traditional uh
uh places so what I mean by that is like
for example
um cognitive behavioral therapy is is
like a science that's very well known in
the psychology field which I minored in
I wouldn't have been exposed to it had I
not gotten that minor and that whole
entire field of study is how you get
somebody to admit they have a problem
and then take action on that problem
so that's literally what cognitive
behavioral therapies whole principle
model is sounds very relevant for a
seller right like yeah when you're
dealing with a buyer or you're dealing
with trying to persuade people to take
action zero zero of the techniques known
in CBT are ever taught in sales and
there's some very core principles that
are just Universal right this is just
basic
um science about how a brain works how
we form decisions and then how we act
upon those decisions and I'm sure if
you're a seller right now you're like
spill the beans that does sound really
yeah
like that there's stuff from
anthropology about
um the the sort of the the the
archetypes of Storytelling that were
never in my sales training and
anthropology has seen across every
culture across every region storytelling
is a core function of culture and there
are patterns to how stories are told
so we're not winging it you know it's
not like stuff you need to make up or
you got to sit there at your desk
sitting in front of like a blank screen
writing a cold email where you gotta
become a poet you don't there's there's
proven methods out there but
unfortunately we're just not taught
those things in our traditional sales
training
yeah absolutely and and you you know
comparing it to uh cognitive behavioral
therapy it's like what if we told a
therapist like hey create urgency for
your client just like we were talking
about right that would never work but
that's not what we're doing yeah
that is not going to give me more
clients at all but
um awesome no and and that's what I'm
excited to talk with you we talked a
little bit about this before we hit
record
um and this is something you talk a lot
about on LinkedIn is following the
buyer's Journey versus maybe like a
seller's Journey so at a high level do
you mind just talking about the stages
and you know how this has helped your
sales career yeah and I'll say this was
like I mean I was probably four years
into my sales career before I even
learned what the buyer's Journey was and
I was just like what why didn't anyone
say this so if you're buying like a
stick of gum a piece of software a house
it doesn't matter you follow five
general stages which is unaware aware
consideration evaluation decision it's
kind of the beat you follow yeah and and
where you are in that those five stages
dictates what you need
so if you're unaware somebody needs to
kind of get you curious and if you're
aware somebody then needs to get your
attention and so on and so forth you go
through each of the stages you can
identify an emotion that you're trying
to get from people
and it really helps you understand the
difference between a Target
a prospect and a buyer and a lot of
sales leaders and sellers use those sort
of words interchangeably and they're not
you know a buyer and a customer are not
the same thing because a customer has
already made a decision a buyer has for
sure
and so when you start making these words
synonyms that are not you're gonna get
yourself all mixed up and what ends up
happening is spending time with people
who are not serious about buying
getting your deal stuck in status quo no
decision yeah and essentially you know
the the worst thing you could do as a
seller is waste your time because for
every minute you spend on somebody who's
not going to buy that's one less minute
you have for somebody who was really
going to buy
and if of all the things that I could
say about Elite sellers that I've seen
over my career that I've worked with and
I've had a chance to work with some
master seller some really quality
sellers the one thing I can say all of
them have in common is they are ruthless
with their time they do not dilly-dally
they don't play games they don't like to
be flung around yeah they want to only
work with people who are dead serious
and then if they are dead serious they
will devote themselves to helping them
yeah but you gotta pass a certain
Benchmark before you get their time and
attention
and uh I think a lot of a lot of sellers
would benefit from that kind of
mentality and that comes from
understanding the buyer's Journey where
is this buyer really at before you can
go spending hours upon hours of time
work and energy
with them
for sure and everything that you just
talked about makes me feel like you're
probably the type of person that
disqualifies faster than
qualifying trying to qualify someone or
fit someone into a box aggressively I I
want to find all the reasons why I
shouldn't work with someone right away
and and that just comes down to asking
very difficult questions
um up front and just being very Frank
with people like you know we're not for
everyone this won't work yeah here are
the reasons why I really think you
should consider this I really understand
why you think this needs to happen now
I'm just I'm trying to understand
why you feel that's such a big problem
and why it became a priority over other
things I'm sure there's a million other
things going on in your life right now
why aren't they the things you want to
talk about I want to push people on
those sort of subjects and and get very
clear answers and if people are
wishy-washy or not feeling very clear or
confident back I'm going to tell them
listen it's just normally this is this
you know like anything in life change
requires commitment and work and I love
that this is the best change for you
right now yeah and and people love that
kind of bluntness I mean I see bad
advice all the time on LinkedIn about
like teaching sellers to walk on
eggshells like classic example I see
people posting all the time like oh if
if you're talking to somebody they're
not the decision maker and you want to
get the decision maker on the next call
say something corny like who would feel
left out if we didn't have her in the
next conversation I'm like or you could
just be really blunt and say in my
experience this product doesn't get
approved without the cfo's approval
early on I just hadn't seen it happen I
doubt you're the exception
what's stopping us from getting the CFO
involved in the next call yeah what
would make you not want to do that
this is very blunt and they're going to
give you a very blunt answer because
you're not walking on eggshells and
trying to like you know formulate this
you know fuzzy question that you don't
need to be asking
yeah a fuzzy question and and as a
seller I mean I have less experience
than you do but what I like to do in my
process is disqualify people early too
and the funny thing is like sometimes
they beg to to keep talking with me like
I'll say hey this doesn't really seem
like this is going to be a fit
um you know and they're like well and
then they just like start trying to
pitch me on why they would be a fit and
I'm like this is this is kind of cool
yeah
because it's a dinette it's a shift in
the dynamic
um yeah you know people don't realize
that and again this is why I'm saying
it's a science not an art you know when
you one of the things they teach in
Psychology is social paradigms so we're
in a social Paradigm right now of guest
and host yep right so you you already
know that it would be rude of me if I
just picked up my phone and started
answering a phone call it's like wait
you're the you're the guest you have to
be present in this conversation you
don't have to tell me that I knew that
but if this was a webinar and I was an
attendee I could totally pick up my
phone and take a phone call and nobody
cared right so we know that there's so
certain social norms in different
settings different environments and so
the the social Paradigm of a buyer
seller is one of conflict one of
competing interests you have one of um
agendas you know and so you want to get
out of that social Paradigm as soon as
you can you don't want to stay in a
buyer seller social it's not a it's not
a positive one yeah you want to get to
something that's like
teacher and student or
um peers or something like that and and
there are ways to do that like I was
taught very early on in my sales career
I used to do outside sales okay so when
you walk into an office and somebody
offered you to get you a drink of water
you always say yes even if you just
drink a bucket of water you say yeah why
because the act of them going to get you
a drink of water is the act of a host
and a guest and that's a much more
positive social Paradigm yeah or so
so you're changing the dynamic a bit and
so what you're describing is when you're
in a setting and all of a sudden the
buyer's pitching you
you know that's a very that's no longer
a buyer seller's social Paradigm you've
changed it yeah and we've changed it by
being adamant and and Frank with them
that this is not in their interest and
now they're like wait I really think it
is that's good that's positive so like I
said there's science behind the stuff
and
I went years not being taught I'm like
how did I sell anything oh my God
no I meant it sits on anything yeah
yeah that's the funny part of it too
it's like I've definitely had some of
those moments where I'm like how did I
do anything in that role before with
having like little to no training at
those spots but somehow we get by in a
certain amount of ways but um cool so
let's let's talk a little bit about the
cold call and how matching this to this
these stages that you talked about so
the cold call would fall under the
unaware aware stage when you're reaching
out to someone so how are sellers kind
of making the mistakes in in this stage
and I've seen you talk about their
they're trying to be the hero in this
stage too
yeah like so the the what what people
are doing wrong what kind of the classic
thing to do is and and this is the
difference between again Elite sellers
um versus average sellers that are doing
this is
people think okay I want to get somebody
on the phone and I need to pitch them
and by pitching them they might be
interested in what I have to offer and
then I'm gonna have a conversation about
that which is totally wrong it doesn't
work that way and you get hung up on a
ton and that's why the number one
objection and I've done this with so
many other groups to asking like what is
the number one objection you face when
you cold call yeah I'm not interested
well I'm not interested isn't an
objection it's a it's a it's a review
it's a negative review thinking like
your pitch was a movie a movie script
and the audience is saying I don't want
to watch that movie I don't like it and
when you think like that you're like
okay well I better change my my script I
need to change what I'm saying because
it's not inviting them to want to have a
conversation so once you realize okay
people I'm calling are in unaware or
aware and what I mean by that is maybe
unaware of a problem maybe unaware of my
company definitely unaware of me so
there's there's multiple levels of
unawareness that they have for sure and
within 30 seconds I want to take them
from unaware
and saying hello to actually having a
conversation with me how am I going to
accomplish that all right what how if
I'm gonna chunk it how do I go from
Hello to meaningful conversation within
30 seconds to a minute with a complete
random stranger well the the truth is
you're not by talking about yourself
yeah there's no way shape or formed
though like I I don't know what the
right answer is to that question but I
can tell you what the wrong answer is
the wrong answer is well I'll talk about
me yeah I'll talk about my company
what I do what we offer and hope to God
that that sounds interesting to them
terrible plan
so now you got to flip it and say well
the best way to get people talking is to
ask them about themselves
sure and
um can I accomplish in the first 30 to
40 seconds of a cold call can I State a
problem that I think is really relevant
with people who are typically in this
role or typically at companies like this
and then ask them a what or how question
some sort of open-ended question about
that yeah see if I can get them to
acknowledge that problem to tell me yeah
that is that is interesting or you
definitely said something that I can
relate to okay
that's the mic drop method so we want to
go permission problem provoke
permission problem sounds like this it
sounds like hey Maggie you're not
expecting my call so you have a moment I
promise to be brief okay uh
um okay sure what's this about
and I'm gonna say something like
I speak to a lot of CFOs of small
businesses and I know that your number
two cost after payroll
is health benefits which have been
rising 9 to 12 percent year over year in
the state of California I'm wondering
how are you handling your second largest
cost Rising that much year over year
and the number one reaction I got
from CFOs code calling them like this
was like wait who is this again because
they were so surprised that I asked them
such a smart
well-formulated question
and 30 seconds of getting a cold call
yeah without hesitation I'd be like oh
this is bilan from trying it and again
I'm I'm calling about your second
largest costs and I'm wondering have you
been experiencing 9 to 12 year-of-year
increases
and how are you handling it and they
would just sort of die bib well we have
a broker and you're right we have been
seeing that kind of stuff and it's been
really frustrating and all of a sudden
we're in the middle of a conversation
yeah
you know and and and so the the key
there is that I stated a problem that I
knew was really relevant for them and
then I asked him a thoughtful question
about how they handle it and the
confidence of that and just the research
that went into that makes them want to
talk
for sure and it's really flipping the
switch from most cool calls that you
hear I don't get a ton but that's like
hey I'm John calling from X and we help
X do y and it's like well first you
already kind of well I guess for us you
already know it's a cold call but I get
I I'm guessing other business
professionals that aren't in sales could
gather that's a cold call too and I
think yeah it's like that that idea of
starting a conversation but I think
that's where you need to you know be
really targeted and really think about
what that question is that you're gonna
ask them right because
you could and that comes from doing
other cold calls or doing research or
getting industry at sites but I think
that's like the key because if you I
don't know like have you ever done those
types of cold calls where you kind of
missed it or yeah and how do those go it
takes testing so the the way you know
you've hit the right mic drop script and
the reason we call the reason I call it
mic drop is because I'm holding the
microphone at the beginning of the call
spotlights on me and I want to get off
center stage and give you the microphone
and then you have your moment so it's
almost like an interview remember we
talked about the social Paradigm yeah
social Paradigm of the mic drop script
is to try to create a paradigm of an
interview versus a cold call cold call
is one of bad right it's a bad initial
Paradigm it's pitching it's unsolicited
right solicitation is bad that's a bad
yeah I want to change it to like oh I'm
actually just interviewing you so I'm
asking you a question so I'm framing a
problem that asks you a question and
going here you go give me the answer and
I'm turning the mic towards you and I'm
gonna get off center stage and give you
the spotlight and let you talk
so that's the goal of it and you're
right there's there's it takes testing
and you can get it completely wrong and
the way you know you're getting it right
is talk time goes up okay so we want
that kind of response from the buyer
where they're either going wait who is
this again because they're so surprised
and pleasantly surprised by by the
quality of the question or they just
start answering it and the way you know
you got it wrong is again you you get
those I'm not interested we had we did
it wrong at bio IQ in the beginning we
typically when I do this we'll come up
with maybe three or four problem
statements okay and we'll test each one
and so when we get the wrong one we
still get that I'm not interested so we
we found out we were calling at the time
um food safety people through bio IQ and
we were getting hung up on a lot and so
um we reached out to a food safety
person that we knew we asked them could
we just interview you just to get some
like Persona research
so it wasn't a sales conversation yeah
and we told them this is our script and
he told us oh no wonder you're getting
hung up on and they're like why and like
these food and safety people probably
think you're a journalist from a local
news
um Welling them yeah and they would
never answer that question because if
they did that might like cause issues
we're like oh my God we went too far
yeah interview yeah all right getting
too deep you must think we're
journalists yeah right yeah it would
never comment on their food safety
procedures to a total stranger okay I
can open them up to liability yeah you
guys got to tone it down yeah
so sometimes you do get it wildly wrong
but
it's it's easy to fix that's just a b
testing yeah and once you do the AV
testing we toned it down and immediately
we started having meaningful
conversations our connect our connect
rate doesn't change but our ability when
we do get a connection have a meaningful
interaction goes through the roof
uh so that that's sort of that's sort of
the process you want to follow and there
are other sometimes like for example I I
give your listeners some some different
ideas to think about sometimes you don't
State a problem you just State the
competition uh we had a product that I
sold and
it was very rare that we spoke to
somebody that didn't use a competitor
gotcha so instead of stating a problem
we just went right in with that we would
say look a lot of wealth advisors use
tools like hidden levers riskalizer
totem to do their risk analysis what are
you using today or are you familiar with
those tools yeah we lift our top three
competitors right in the first 10
seconds of the cold call and people be
like yeah yeah I've heard of risk lies
or yeah we we just got off totem we hate
it yeah I don't understand you're having
a conversation
about that and I think that's where it
comes in of like the the companies we've
probably both worked for of like being
early stage startups and you know people
not knowing your name but using the
competitors names like the big Goliath
and in the space because yeah we're in a
similar position with mailshake like we
compete with sales Austin Outreach who
hasn't tested out one of those tools or
who doesn't know what those are
um but it's funny because about three
years ago or maybe a little bit before
some people weren't aware of the two big
competitors out there so we did have to
that wasn't really our pitch back then
or or like go in question I shouldn't
say pitch but that wasn't really our
going question when we were prospecting
um but now it totally is because most
people are aware of it so I love that
because yeah you're it's like taking
those two angles and it's like
one is unaware and then the aware part
of it too of testing out and mentioning
the competitor's name as well so I think
that's pretty cool and and one part of
it like your um your mic drop cold call
pitch is is the permission based opener
and I kind of see this as like a heated
debate nowadays but I guess like what's
your argument for using one
um just because I've heard people that
don't use them
I mean so I was taught that I know
you're not expecting a call do you have
a moment I promise to be brief in like
2010. okay I was taught I was taughted
by MJ Hoffman who used to run a program
called your sales MBA so he was using
that literally like a decade ago and and
even well before that so like permission
based open it's funny people think it's
like something new yeah that's just like
this has been around for a very long
time before some of us were even born
people have been cold calling that kind
of stuff and it works
and it works and if if you find one that
you like go for it I've always enjoyed
that one because I'm not trying to be
funny
I'm not trying to be I'm not trying to
belittle myself and say I'm sorry I'm
cold calling you or anything like that
I'm not inviting them to hang up I don't
like saying that because I'm like who
are you to hang up on me all right I
have rights too yeah it's like cold it
doesn't mean you can you can hang up on
me so yeah I like that one because I
think it's respectful it's tempered and
it's direct and I prefer just to be very
direct if I'm cold calling somebody for
sure and the fans would be like you know
what I didn't you're right I'm not
expecting this call and I don't want it
I'm like okay no problem when we move on
with our lives cool so that's the one I
prefer yeah I think there's some
permission-based openers that I've seen
that I I frown upon because I'm like you
know
that's not I think that's diluting the
point of the of what that is yeah and
for those that don't use it and they're
totally fine well who's to stop you then
I mean look at the end of the day do you
you know so if you if you don't like it
and you just want to go straight into
um you know like some sort of a mic drop
script without any permission go for it
I just think that
if you ever have gotten a cold call
the first thing you're trying to figure
out is it's typically an unknown number
yeah first thing I'm trying to figure
out is what is this is this like is this
like a family member in an emergency is
this
um something related to work that I need
to know you're just trying to support
yourself out in the first few seconds of
a call like what is this and categorize
it so I want to make that really easy
for people and that's what my personal
permission based opener does it just
tells them look it's not an expected
call
I am about to pitch you or you gotta get
more minute cool if you're not totally
fine awesome yeah Fila thanks so much
for going through you know that
permission based opener and I think
you're right it's it's not something new
like you said it's been something that's
been around for a while anyways so it's
like
yeah I I think it's just a normal way to
sort of call in general so just to
finish things up
um you know we talked a lot about you
know the buyer stage we talked about how
when you're actually making cold calls
it's going to be the unaware aware stage
um and I guess just to kind of end it
here like what are like one or two
things that you find you see sales reps
do that are pretty fluffy when it comes
to cold calling
yeah there's a few I mean again the the
the pitching in the first 30 seconds
doesn't make a ton of sense I mean if
you're getting a lot of I'm not
interested it's because you're not
interesting so just change it up yeah
and gotta find something that's going to
pique their interest and what are you
really trying to accomplish in the first
30 seconds of the cold calls just to get
some curiosity from them get get them
talking
and and that's you know you gotta ask
them a thoughtful question if you want
to get people talking that's about them
not about you so yeah they'll do that
and the second thing is
um it's really tempting to use the word
help
I think if I could ban one word if we
did Mouse it'd be the word help yeah
people don't want help nobody's asking
for on you know unsolicited Uninvited
help
uh you know
it it doesn't feel nice when you add
when people are asking you know offering
you help when you don't need it you'd be
like for sure you can help me what like
calm nothing you know back off I'm fine
um
change that mentality because when you
say we help or I help blink with blank
what you're saying is I'm the hero and I
can save you yeah and you want your
buyer to be the hero not you
the hero of the story the knight in
shining armor is the buyer and you my
dear sellers are Merlin
and you are a secondary character and it
hurts and does it it doesn't make sense
because we're normally the stars of our
own lives but in this case you were the
secondary character
and you are there to give the knight in
shining armor the magic sword to slay
the dragon
you're not slaying the dragon so you
gotta let them play that role so when
you remove the word help and you start
talking about their problems and their
issues and getting them to acknowledge
that they have those problems and issues
embracing those problems and issues then
you can tell them
well we have found that others like you
have been able to tackle those problems
and issues by trying things like blank
and those things that they try happen to
be what your product or offering is
okay and now all of a sudden you're not
saying how you help people but you're
telling them they accomplished they they
were victorious
and we happen to have the the sword that
they use to slay that Dragon would you
want to try that sword on yourself
yeah
for sure because when you think about it
in B2B like what's the goal of the buyer
in that scenario they want to look good
to their company they're in a role where
they report to someone most likely where
they want to make a good impression so
if they bring in this tool if we're
talking about SAS
then they want to make sure that this is
something that's going to help like
multiple people in their organization
solve a problem or save them money in
that scenario so I love it be
interesting remove the word help totally
agree with you created the word help
it's hard
it's hard but just cut that word out
find another way to say that sentence
without the word help and you'll find
you're making a better quality
conversation by not talking about how
you've helped yeah it's also just so
overused that I kind of tune out once I
hear it just kind of me but I definitely
do
um awesome thank you so so much for
being on here today and talking about
removing fluff just from the sales
process and also from cold calling in
general to finish up where can people
find you or learn more about you yeah so
I'm posting daily on LinkedIn just from
the journey and experience so you could
find it there and I just started my
newsletter so if you want to sign up to
that it's on a website called nos.io
which is nas.io death to fluff so you
can find it there and sign up and get
the tips uh directly in your inbox or uh
on your phone
amazing amazing yeah I'm super excited
to take a look at what it's going to
look like on my phone below thank you so
so much again for being here thank you
awesome all right we'll catch everyone
next time on Shake sales bye
[Music]